<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY rfc6797 SYSTEM
"http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6797.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc7626 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7626.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc7858 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7858.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.ietf-dprive-dtls-and-tls-profiles SYSTEM
"http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-dprive-dtls-and-tls-profiles.xml">
]>

<rfc docName="draft-bortzmeyer-dprive-step-2-00-BETA"
     category="std" ipr="trust200902">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc strict="yes"?>
<front>
<title abbrev="DPRIVE step 2">Next step for DPRIVE: resolver-to-auth link</title>
<author fullname="Stephane Bortzmeyer" initials="S." surname="Bortzmeyer">
<organization>AFNIC</organization>
<address><postal><street>1, rue Stephenson</street><code>78180</code><city>Montigny-le-Bretonneux</city><country>France</country></postal> <phone>+33 1 39 30 83 46</phone><email>bortzmeyer+ietf@nic.fr</email><uri>http://www.afnic.fr/</uri></address>
</author>
<date month="TODO" year="TODO"/>
<abstract>
  <t>This document examines the possible future work for the DPRIVE
  (DNS privacy) working group, specially in securing the
  resolver-to-authoritative name server link.</t>
  <t>It is not intended to be published as a RFC.</t>
<t>REMOVE BEFORE PUBLICATION: this document should be discussed in the
IETF DPRIVE group, through its mailing list. The
source of the document, as well as a list of open issues, is currently
kept <eref
target="https://github.com/bortzmeyer/ietf-dprive-step-2">at Github</eref>.</t>
</abstract>
</front>

<middle>
  <section anchor="intro" title="Introduction and background">
    <t>To improve the privacy of the DNS user (<xref
    target="RFC7626"/>), the standard solution is to encrypt the
    requests with TLS (<xref target="RFC7858"/>). Just encrypting,
    without authenticating the remote server, leaves the user's
    privacy vulnerable to active man-in-the-middle attacks. <xref
    target="RFC7858"/> and <xref
target="I-D.ietf-dprive-dtls-and-tls-profiles"/> describe how to
    authenticate the DNS resolver, in the stub-to-resolver link. We
    have currently no standard way to authenticate the authoritative
    name server, in the resolver-to-auth link.</t>
    <t>The two cases are quite different: a stub resolver has only a
    few resolvers, and there is typically a pre-existing
    relationship. But a resolver speaks to many authoritative name
    servers, without any prior relationship. This means that, for
    instance, having a static key for the resolver makes sense while
    it would be clearly unrealistic for the authoritative server.</t>
    <t>TODO DPRIVE charter's limits</t>
  </section>

  <section title="Possible solutions">
    <t>Here is a comprehensive list of the possible solutions to the
    problem of authenticating the authoritative DNS server. TODO subsections?</t>
    <t>We could encode the key in the authoritative server name (as in
    DNScurve TODO ref).</t>
    <figure><artwork>
% dig +short NS yp.to
uz5dz39x8xk8wyq3dzn7vpt670qmvzx0zd9zg4ldwldkv6kx9ft090.ns.yp.to.
uz5hjgptn63q5qlch6xlrw63tf6vhvvu6mjwn0s31buw1lhmlk14kd.ns.yp.to.
uz5uu2c7j228ujjccp3ustnfmr4pgcg5ylvt16kmd0qzw7bbjgd5xq.ns.yp.to.     
    </artwork></figure>
    <t>Transmitting the key would therefore be a
    by-product of delegation. TODO limits in number of name servers, in
    name's length for RSA.</t>
    <t>We could publish keys in the DNS, secured with DNSSEC (as in
    DANE TODO ref). This 
  raises an interesting bootstrap problem: we need to have an
  "unsecure" mode to retrieve the initial key material.</t>
   <t>We could simply not check the keys at all, accepting anything.</t>
   <t>We could use the X.509 security model TODO ref (RFC
   PKIX?). Certificates for authoritative name servers, signed by
regular CAs, with the IP address of the server in the Subject
Alternative Name. (TODO how many CAs accept that?)</t>
   <t>all these solutions can be improved by solutions like automatic key
pinning (<xref target="RFC6797"/>).
</t>
  </section>
    
<section title="IANA Considerations">
<t>TODO</t>
</section>

<section anchor="security" title="Security Considerations">
<t>TODO</t>
</section>

<section title="Acknowledgments">
<t>TODO</t>
</section>

</middle>

<back>

<references title='Normative References'>
  &rfc7858;
  &I-D.ietf-dprive-dtls-and-tls-profiles;
</references>

<references title='Informative References'>
  &rfc6797;
  &rfc7626;
</references> 

</back>

</rfc>



